<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ns2:code cars="" id="P0113" xmlns:ns2="com.queeq.odbq.errorcodes">
    <meanings>
        <meaning rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">The powertrain control module (PCM) monitors the temperature of the air entering the engine. The PCM supplies a 5 volt reference voltage to the Intake Air Temperature (IAT) sensor. The IAT is a thermistor that varies resistance based on temperature. As the temperature increases, resistance decreases. Low temperature results in a high signal voltage. When the PCM sees a signal voltage higher than 5 volts, it sets this P0113 check engine light code.</meaning>
    </meanings>
    <causes>
        <cause rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">Faulty connection at IAT sensor</cause>
        <cause rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">Faulty PCM (less likely but not impossible)</cause>
        <cause rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">IAT harness and/or wiring routed too close to highvoltage wiring (e.g. alternator, spark plug cables, etc.)</cause>
        <cause rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">Internally failed IAT sensor</cause>
        <cause rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">Open in IAT ground circuit or signal circuit</cause>
        <cause rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">Short to voltage in IAT signal circuit or reference circuit</cause>
    </causes>
    <descriptions>
        <description rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">Intake Air Temperature Circuit High Input</description>
    </descriptions>
    <solutions>
        <solution rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">First, if you have access to a scan tool, is there an IAT reading? If the IAT reading is logical then the problem is likely intermittent. If the reading is less than 30 degrees, unplug the connector. Install a jumper wire between the harness connector signal and ground circuits. The IAT temperature reading on the scan tool should be maxed out at the high end. For example it should be 280 degrees Farenheit or higher. If it is, the wiring is okay, and it may have been the connection. If it isn't install the jumper wire between the IAT signal circuit and the chassis ground.If now the IAT reading on the scan tool is maxed out then check for an open in the IAT ground circuit. If you get no reading at all on the scan tool, it's likely that the sensor signal is open or the 5 volt reference is missing. Check using a DVOM (digital volt ohm meter) for a 5 volt reference. If it's there, then unplug the connector at the PCM and check for continuity on the IAT signal circuit between the PCM connector and the IAT connector.Other IAT sensor and circuit related DTCs: P0095, P0096, P0097, P0098, P0099, P0109, P0110, P0111, P0112, P0114</solution>
    </solutions>
    <references/>
    <symptoms>
        <symptom rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">There will likely be no symptoms other than illumination of the Malfunction Indicator Lamp (MIL  Check Engine Light / Service Engine Soon).</symptom>
    </symptoms>
</ns2:code>
