<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ns2:code cars="" id="P0172" xmlns:ns2="com.queeq.odbq.errorcodes">
    <meanings>
        <meaning rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">Basically this means that an oxygen sensor in bank 1 detected a rich condition (too little oxygen in the exhaust). On V6/V8/V10 engines, Bank 1 is the side of the engine that has cylinder #1.Note: This DTC is very similar to P0175, and in fact your vehicle may show both codes at the same time.</meaning>
    </meanings>
    <causes>
        <cause rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">The MAF (Mass Air Flow) Sensor is dirty or faulty. Note: The use of oiled air filters can cause the MAF to become dirty if the filter is overoiled. There is also an issue with some vehicles where the MAF sensors leak the silicone potting material used to protect the circuitry.</cause>
        <cause rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">There could be a fuel pressure or delivery problem</cause>
        <cause rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">There could be a vacuum leak.</cause>
    </causes>
    <descriptions>
        <description rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">System Too Rich (Bank 1)</description>
    </descriptions>
    <solutions>
        <solution rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">Check for an exhaust leak before the first oxygen sensor (this is unlikely to cause the problem, but it is possible)</solution>
        <solution rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">Check the fuel injectors, they may be dirty. Use fuel injector cleaner or get them professionally cleaned/replaced.</solution>
        <solution rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">Check the fuel pressure at the fuel rail</solution>
        <solution rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">Cleanthe MAF sensor. Consult your service manual for it's location if you need help. I find it's best to take it off and spray it with electronics cleaner or brake cleaner. Make sure you are careful not to damage the MAF sensor, and make sure it's dry before reinstalling</solution>
        <solution rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">Inspect all vacuum and PCV hoses, replace if necessary</solution>
        <solution rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">Inspect fuel lines for cracks, leaks, or pinches</solution>
    </solutions>
    <references/>
    <symptoms>
        <symptom rtPlus="0" rtNeutral="0" rtMinus="0">You will more than likely not notice any drivability problems, although there may be symptoms such as a misfire.</symptom>
    </symptoms>
</ns2:code>
